{"tossups": [{"question": "This trail was first mapped by Walter Goodwin, but it closed for five decades until Joe Redington Jr. could find a way to clear out the snow. Gunnar Kaasen traversed this trail during the Great Race of Mercy. In 1925, a diphtheria-stricken town was saved by a crucial serum run on this trail whose final leg was led by Balto, a Siberian Husky. For the point, name this historic trail that connected Seward and Nome over hundreds of miles of Alaskan wilderness and is commemorated by an annual dog sled race.", "answer": "<b> Iditarod</b> Trail (accept<b> Seward-to-Nome</b> Trail before \u201cSeward\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Yozma tax incentive program was created by this politician, who died while ironically carrying a paper with a song telling how it is impossible to bring a dead person back to life. This leader crushed Palestinian resistance with the \u201cIron Fist\u201d policy during the First Intifada. Operation Thunderbolt on Entebbe Airport was ordered by this Prime Minister, who joined Shimon Peres and Yasser Arafat as 1994 Nobel Peace Prize laureates. Golda Meir was succeeded by, for the point, what Prime Minister of Israel who was assassinated in 1995?", "answer": "Yitzhak<b> Rabin</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ruler is believed to be the subject of the Streatham and Houghton portraits, two works that may have been recreated after this ruler\u2019s death. After being deposed, this monarch was aided at the execution by Sir Thomas Brydges and was added to<em> Foxe\u2019s Book of Martyrs</em>, a Protestant propaganda book. In a painting of this ruler by Paul Delaroche, she kneels in white and reaches hesitantly for the chopping block that was used for her execution in the Tower of London in 1554 on the orders of Mary I [first]. For the point, name this \u201cNine Days\u2019 Queen\u201d who briefly succeeded Edward VI [sixth] as queen of England.", "answer": "Lady Jane<b> Grey</b> (accept Jane<b> Dudley</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The losing vice-presidential candidate in this election year was a newspaper magnate who later served as Secretary of the Navy. James Farley punned on the phrase \u201cas Maine goes, so goes the nation\u201d in this election year, whose losing candidate wasn\u2019t saved by the endorsement of Jesse Owens. In this election year, a Kansas governor lost in a landslide, 523 to 8 in the Electoral College. For the point, name this year in which Alf Landon lost the presidential election to incumbent Franklin D. Roosevelt.", "answer": "US presidential election of<b> 1936</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Before conning gold miners in the Klondike, \u201cSoapy\u201d Smith operated a prize soap racket in this city. Jonathan Cox and William Larimer founded this city at the confluence of Cherry Creek and the South Platte River. In 1972, this city became the first, and so far only, city to decline an invitation to host the Olympic Games. The \u201cCarnation Gold Rush\u201d took place in this largest city in the Front Range Corridor, whose suburbs include Littleton and Aurora. The Pike\u2019s Peak Gold Rush triggered the settlement of, for the point, what capital city of Colorado?", "answer": "<b> Denver</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Hank Stram coached this team to victory in Super Bowl 4, the last game before the NFL-AFL merger. The record for loudest crowd in an outdoor stadium was set in 2014 at this team\u2019s Arrowhead Stadium. Andy Reid coaches and Patrick Mahomes plays for, for the point, what NFL team in western Missouri?", "answer": "<b> Kansas City Chiefs</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The documentary<em> A Film Unfinished</em> details an unfinished propaganda film focusing on this location. A Heroes\u2019 Monument in this location was ironically built with materials that Albert Speer planned to use. Mordechai Anielewicz [an-yell-eh-vitch] led a resistance organization that was put down by J\u00a8urgen Stroop during a 1943 uprising in this location; many of the survivors were sent to the Treblinka extermination camp. Over 400,000 Jews were forced to live in, for the point, what location, the largest of its kind, in the capital of Poland?", "answer": "<b> Warsaw ghetto</b> (prompt on Warsaw and other partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A ruler of these people led a Pacific Ocean expedition and supposedly found the \u201cfire\u201d and \u201couter\u201dbelt. Qullqa warehouses were built by this empire, whose rulers included Topa and Pachacuti. Upon being given a Bible, a ruler of this empire failed to realize its use and began the Battle of Cajamarca; that ruler filed the Ransom Room with gold. Atahualpa led, for the point, what empire based at Cuzco in the Andes Mountains of Peru?", "answer": "<b> Inca</b>n Empire (accept<b> Inca</b>s)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A rival of this leader, Blucher Philogenes, was decapitated and had his head packed into a pail of ice so this leader could talk with it. This ruler told his militia to hunt down black dogs because he believed Clement Barbot could transform into one. The Tonton Macoute helped enforce this man\u2019s rule, which was propped up by a cult of personality in which this man claimed to be a loa spirit from Voodoo culture. This man\u2019s son Jean-Claude succeeded him after his 1971 death. For the point, name this dictator of Haiti.", "answer": "<b> F</b>ran\u00b8cois<b> Duvalier</b> (accept<b> Papa Doc</b> Duvalier; prompt on Duvalier)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A race riot in this state was instigated by Charles B. Aycock, who was later elected governor of this state with the help of the \u201cSecret Nine.\u201d Clarence \u201cCurly\u201d Harris refused to serve protesting students in this state, where Alfred Waddell burned down<em> The Daily Record</em>, a newspaper owned by African-American Alexander Manly, during an 1898 race riot. Black students from A&T University conducted a protest at a Woolworth\u2019s counter in, for the point, what state, the site of the 1989 Wilmington insurrection and the Greensboro sit-in?", "answer": "<b> North Carolina</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A prominent musician claimed that if this city\u2019s Stavisky riots prevented her students from attending their private lessons, they weren\u2019t cut out for music anyway. The composer of<em> Pell\u00b4eas et M\u00b4elisande</em> was denied a public funeral in this city due to bombing in World War I. A 1926 visit to Maurice Ravel inspired George Gershwin to include taxi horns in a concerto titled<em> An American in</em> this city.<em> The Rite of Spring</em> infamously premiered in, for the point, what home of Nadia Boulanger and Claude Debussy, the French capital city?", "answer": "<b> Paris</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Francis Hopkinson helped revitalize a society that this man founded with members of his Leather Apron Club. This founder of the American Philosophical Society hired Lewis Timothy as the first librarian in America. Temperance and silence are among the thirteen virtues described in this man\u2019s autobiography. The glass harmonica and bifocals were among the inventions of, for the point, what Philadelphia Founding Father, the first U.S. Ambassador to France?", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Franklin</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The<em> Newport</em> controversially slipped past the<em> Aigle</em>, taking the record of being the first vessel to pass through this waterway. Plans for this waterway to change hands were made during the Protocol of Sevres. Because of the dust they accumulated, a fleet of ships trapped by the closure of this waterway became known as the \u201cYellow Fleet.\u201d Anthony Eden was forced to resign after authorizing a paratrooper attack on this waterway. Gamal Abdel Nasser nationalized, for the point, what Egyptian waterway that links the Mediterranean and Red Seas?", "answer": "<b> Suez Canal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this conflict, Henry Pate was captured at the Battle of Black Jack and subsequently exchanged for the winning commander\u2019s two imprisoned sons. Sharps rifles known as \u201cBeecher\u2019s Bibles\u201d were delivered during this conflict. Failed attempts to resolve this conflict included the Lecompton Constitution and Topeka Constitution. John Brown perpetrated the Pottawatomie Massacre during, for the point, what 1850s conflict in which border ruffians and free-staters fought over a popular sovereignty vote in a Midwest state?", "answer": "<b> Bleeding Kansas</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The most decorated unit in US military history, the 442nd Regiment, was almost solely comprised of this ethnic group during World War II. A Gentlemen\u2019s Agreement between two governments allowed this ethnic group to immigrate to the US, bypassing the Chinese Exclusion Act. The Supreme Court affirmed the ability to persecute these people in<em> Korematsu v. United States</em>. For the point, name this ethnic minority that was imprisoned in American internment camps during World War II.", "answer": "<b> Japanese</b>-Americans", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A public health insurance program in this state is called \u201cDr. Dynasaur.\u201d This state was once governed by a man whose odd scream after the Iowa caucus hurt his 2004 presidential campaign. This state, once led by Howard Dean, is home to the longest-serving independent in congressional history, a man who won 23 Democratic primaries and caucuses in 2016. For the point, name this New England state represented by Senators Patrick Leahy and Bernie Sanders.", "answer": "<b> Vermont</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "These men were known for carrying a large vessel known as the Kazan pot during the communal<em> pilav</em> meal. These men were rivals of the Sipahi, who helped Mahmud II disband this group in the Auspicious Incident in 1826. These men were recruited via the devshirme system, in which Christian boys would be kidnapped from their homes as a blood tax. For the point, name this elite unit of Ottoman infantrymen.", "answer": "<b> Janissary</b> corps (accept<b> Janissaries</b>; prompt on descriptions of Christian Ottoman soldiers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This book contains the Song of the Sea, believed to be one of the oldest portions of the Bible. In this book, a man flees to Midian after killing a slavedriver. This book, whose central figure is told to remove his sandals when he approaches the Burning Bush, details ten plagues on Egypt that occur when Pharaoh refuses to release the Hebrews. Archaeologists have found little evidence in the Sinai region to support the historicity of, for the point, what second book of the Old Testament, which describes Moses leading the Israelites out of Egypt?", "answer": "Book of<b> Exodus</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This man popularized the theory of revolutionary defeatism after heading the leftist faction at the Zimmerwald Conference. This man, who developed the concept of democratic centralism to keep party unity, split with Julius Martov over disagreements about the role of the professional revolutionary. This man theorized how a socialist state would develop in his book<em> The State and</em> <em>the Revolution</em>. The Provisional Government was overthrown by, for the point, what Bolshevik leader who led the first Soviet government?", "answer": "Vladimir<b> Lenin</b> (or Vladimir Ilyich<b> Ulyanov</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}